Veronika Romero

Email: dr.veronika.romero@gmail.com | LinkedIn | GitHub | Google Scholar | Website

Professional Summary

Mission-driven scientist with 15+ years in biomedical research. Passionate about data analysis and visualization of complex datasets. Curiosity-driven critical thinker picking up new concepts and techniques quickly. Problem-solver who can bridge disciplines, engage with colleagues from diverse backgrounds, and optimize workflows.

Education

PhD analogue in Pathophysiology

Bogomoletz Institute of Physiology, Kyiv, Ukraine — 2011-2015

Doctor of Medicine in General Medicine

Bogomolets National Medical University, Kyiv, Ukraine — 2005-2011

Biostatistics | Medical informatics | Epidemiology | Social medicine, healthcare organization and economics

Professional Experience

University of Utah, Salt Lake City, UT

Research Scientist / Laboratory Manager

September 2023 - October 2024

- Analyzed genomic datasets (single-cell and bulk RNA-seq) aimed to establish future research directions.
- Developed R scripts and reporting workflows for reproducible ETL, analysis and visualizations of the data.

Senior Laboratory Specialist / Laboratory Manager

March 2021 – September 2023

- Assisted in establishing and implementing the workflows for laboratory procedures and data analysis.
- Troubleshooted multiple protocols including sample preparation for genomic applications.

Research Fellow

July 2018 - June 2020

Collected, analyzed, and presented data.

Bogomoletz Institute of Physiology, Kyiv, Ukraine

Junior Research Fellow

November 2015 – August 2018

- Collaborated with clinical researchers on the projects in the field of cardiovascular diseases.
- Contributed to experiments, analyzed and visualized data, co-authored 3 shiny apps and 2 publications.

Graduate Research Fellow / PhD student

August 2011 – November 2015

Analyzed, visualized, and interpretated experimental data. Prepared 5 research papers.

Laboratory Technician

May 2009 - August 2011

Contributed to multiple projects resulting in 6 research papers and multiple abstracts.

BioLabTech Ltd., Kyiv, Ukraine

Product Manager

December 2016 - June 2017

- Trained and provided product support to the customers in the field of genomics and medical genetics.
- Presented to the audiences of different backgrounds ranging from 1-on-1 to hundreds of participants.

Bogomolets National Medical University, Kyiv, Ukraine

Teaching Associate

August 2011 - October 2013

Taught seminars and labs to medical students, explained complex concepts at different depth levels.

Technical Skills

- Data Wrangling and Analysis Tools: R, Python, SQL, SPSS, Excel
- Data Visualization: R (ggplot2, shiny), Python (Matplotlib, Seaborn), Tableau
- Statistical Methods: correlation, linear and logistic regression, Kolmogorov-Smirnov test, t-test, Wilcoxon, Mann-Whitney, Kruskal-Wallis tests, ANOVA, chi-square, Fisher's exact test, Kaplan Meier Analysis, etc
- Machine Learning: Dimensionality Reduction, Random Forest, Clustering, k-NN, Regression
- Other Tools: Quarto, MS Office, front-end web development, Adobe Photoshop & Illustrator

Certification

Business Data Analytics professional program from Utah Valley University — November 2020

Languages

English (fluent), Ukrainian (native), russian (native), German (beginner)

Leadership

- 2016-2018: Established and organized scientific seminars, workshops, and conferences in computational biology and precision medicine. It involved dozens of speakers, hundreds of participants, dozens of sponsors, thousands of raised dollars, as well as end-to-end logistics of 8 smaller and two major events:
 - o Integrative Biology & Medicine
 - o single-cell RNABIO & organoids
- 2008-2013: Led a pathophysiology interest group at the Bogomolets National Medical University first as a student and then as a member of the teaching faculty.
- Taught multiple R and Python intro workshops to diverse audiences. Co-authored a manual on R for Data Analysis (Ukrainian). Contributed to multiple syllabuses of courses teaching data science.
- Mentored and trained students of different levels.
- Received a young investigator award from the National Academy of Sciences of Ukraine.

Volunteer Experience

- 2022 joined a team initiating the urgent support and remote opportunities for researchers in Ukraine upon the beginning of full-scale war. It resulted in new policies and programs (Chhugani et al., Science, 2022).
- 2014-2017: volunteer at the scientific outreach events in Ukraine
- 2016-2018 on volunteer bases, end-to-end organization of scientific events in Ukraine

Selected workshops and conferences

- (audit) Computational Genomics class (prof. Aaron Quinlan). University of Utah. 2024
- de.NBI Summer School Computational genomics and RNA Biology, Berlin, Germany, 2017
- RECOMB 2018, Research in Computational Molecular Biology, Paris, France. 2018
- The Non-Coding Genome EMBO|EMBL Symposium, Heidelberg, Germany. 2013

References

Available upon request.